hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference guest stream number
66.1 on December 6th
2023 today we are very excited and
honored to have a presentation and
discussion with Adrien Bon first in this
session Susan Hasty is going to provide
some slides and context Adrien will
provide a talk and we'll have a
discussion on through the hour and then
Susan and I will stay on the live stream
so if you have any comments or questions
please feel free to write them so thank
you both for joining and Susan to
you thank you Daniel um and um and I'm
so excited um and thank you so much uh
for affording this opportunity Dr bang
um um I thought that we would actually
be
again um uh I wanted to introduce you
and as I was thinking about it I could
spend probably the entire time just
going over all the citations and awards
that you've received and so I thought
though that what I really wanted to
share was um was something that is not
necessarily in the public domain um I
wanted to really dig into the
significance of of the Constructor law
um and the difference it's made um not
only for I think the world which most
people um don't appreciate I think and
and also the significance has made for
me um it's definitely changing
paradigms um across across the globe um
this of course is um is Adrian's many uh
many Publications and his many citations
I think think there's 990,000 citations
of his work alone um to
date uh and um but what I'd like for the
audience to really take away is um is
really thinking about uh life in a new
paradigm and how the Constructor law can
inform us of um of how to think about a
difference in not only just what is life
uh but also what is power and what is
evolution and change and and and and
I'll give you a good example um of uh we
we we will talk about a flow Paradigm a
flow architecture and in thinking about
architecture um one one idea that still
permeates society and I think holds back
Progressive how we think about um
hierarchy and Adrian's books has
definitely informed me um to think very
differently you know we we still think
about hierarchy um like we built them um
in pyramids 4,500 years ago you know
where we housed dead people and so this
actually has a has the potential to
change that and to really think
differently um one thing that a lot of
people don't realize is is that
um scientists from around the globe have
been coming together for over 14 years
annually um and presenting their
findings and um and how they've taken
this and spread it into every domain
imaginable um this was actually a uh a
doctor Dr Lucia who's I believe he's in
Italy he shared with me just last night
uh in talking about about it and how
he's actually taken the constructal law
and made Innovations in research in
cancer and I thought his quote was just
so powerful in terms of how we think
differently about reality by really
understanding and going very deep um and
contemplating how the Constructor law um
is is so
significant um this actually
what what I think is is um what is what
I've discovered and
uncovered um is is that it's actually
spread far
beyond the halls of
Academia um and I'm going to make a bold
prediction because we're going to be
talking about predictions and I'm going
to predict that uh Dr bang ban will be
awarded the Nobel Prize because because
it's not just the citations that of his
work but when we look at and you go deep
you're going to find that this the
people are using the constructal law for
example yeah this this one academic
paper has already had um a many many
citations in and of itself um you know
it's being talked about in terms of
religion and in terms of indigenous
societies it's impacted architectures in
how um airports and how structures are
being made um and for me personally um
I'm not coming out of Academia but but
reading it and understanding The
Constructor law really has given me an
incredible all and appreciation for
science it's actually given me a new
appreciation for life um and and so
here's just a few of the ways that um
that chat GTP just put together here is
how it's already spawned new ways of
thinking about every area um of um of of
application and
Innovation uh and and so um what we're
going to be talking about today is
really focused on uh adrianne's books
that are accessible to people like me I
mean I would not been able to dig into
the the many many
Publications um and receive the the uh
the depth of understanding of it without
reading these books and I actually
called them um um
um the um the essence of strategic
thinking because when we think about
prediction we are thinking about how
we're strategically going to move
forward so today we're going to focus on
the physics of life and Adrien has
agreed to uh to give us another chance
so we may not be able to cover all the
many questions that have come through
our Forum but we will be digging into
them um after after he after we'll dig
into some of them that come in on the
chat today um and and then we will also
be exploring them in a future in future
session so so with that I'll turn it
over to you Adrian and um and I look
forward to this and I hope the audience
really enjoys this and and as inspired
as I've
been
see
okay yeah thank you uh Susan and Daniel
for the um invitation to to speak to
your
audience of course I'm very grateful and
humbled by the
introduction um the um I thought that um
in order to to get the discussion going
it would help if I show you a few
Concepts black on
white and the slides I I happen to have
at my disposal are from a very brief
lecture I gave at the Third Constructor
law conference in Ty in Italy just two
months ago um it was a lecture about
vascular flow structures but the the um
the me of the um presentation is about
how to predict the design Evolution uh
vascular is in fact um a good title for
the subject that interests your audience
namely how the the brain works uh the
brain is eminently a vascular
architecture it is predictable from The
Constructor law in in many ways um in
many respects so
um okay and so I um I start my
presentation first of all with the
definition of the meaning the meaning of
the words I am I'm a professor meaning I
teach students to uh um how to think and
uh how to question themselves and how to
to display humility humility when
hearing
ideas um and so the meaning of the word
vascular from Latin is something that
looks like um vessels conveying blood or
lymph uh this is a a design an
architecture that's uh that speaks of
flow flow which means movement and
hierarchy which as you'll see very soon
is one kind of drawing and now now uh
the word design should not scare anybody
in who is in love with science design is
poo pooed in physics um it shouldn't be
because it really means the drawing
drawing uh it came into English from
French Desa uh the French got it from
the Italians dieno it really means a
sign an image that conveys a message and
here I um have I just ja jaos
the two versions of the same drawing a
river Delta and the human lung to drive
the point
that the um the the drawing unites the
animate with the
inanimate and when the drawing does that
it means that uh the phenomenon that the
drawing represents Belongs To Nature not
to a particular compartment in science
or a particular department on the
University
campus uh the drawing unites uh and that
is uh if there is one single message
from my introduction here it is that um
another thing about um um what I'm
showing you is
that natural things are physical
physical they're observable visible
palpable measurable and movable they are
common sense they are not jargon I speak
of drawings of architecture of images uh
natural things have
configuration shape structure Rhythm
they have flow and and they their mother
is the fact that they have freedom to
change that means they have freedom to
evolve and
um um about the uh let's call it uh the
freedom to evolve comes from the fact
that these things are moving
uh they're moving because they are set
in motion by flow architectures that
function as
engines most most of these engines are
natural only a few of them are
human-made in any case um every single
such engine is driven by one kind of
energy source you can think about the
sun driving the movement of the
atmosphere the atmosphere is a Globe
size engine the engine produces power
and the power drives
movement and um while the movement uh is
uh is the source of another phenomenon
which is called dissipation or friction
because the Mover has to get the
environment out of the out of the way
the environment the niche does not get
out of the way unless it is pushed and
in the rectangular box I show the engine
driven by an energy source the work or
power produced by the engine and then
the fact that in the green brakes or
interfaces between mover and environment
are dissipating the power so if you sum
up these white fat arrows uh the energy
input from the energy source is dumped
100 100% into the environment but in the
meantime Inside the Box because of flow
architecture something was moved from
one spot one place to another that
phenomenon is called Locomotion it could
be animal it could be vehicular it could
be well current and all the other things
we we know about so the bottom line is
that nature is movement with low
architecture that um unites really
unites the geophysical with the
biological with the social organization
which is emotion uh these are images
that change over time they are not the
still art there are you think of them as
movies many many movies running uh at
the same time at the same time but every
single one having the same plot the plot
is that the movie has Direction meaning
the changes have a directionality to
them and I Rec recognize this uh
published it first in 1996 several times
then um it's called the construct the
law of evolution in nature um or meaning
the announcement that Hey listen it's
the design in nature stupid uh has been
overlooked in everywhere physics
theonomics uh but not in
engineering which is my uh my background
um so I wrote that for a flow system to
persist in time and that's the
definition definition of the life state
it must evolve with freedom such that it
provides greater access I illustrate
that with three drawings from the
evolution of a river Bas on the floor of
laboratory uh from time to time the um
the architecture
flows more and more easily because of
erosion um and but at every uh point in
time the the uh the tree sorry the the
River Basin is a tree
um The Constructor law announces
probably screaming from the rooftops
that there is a direction of uh of
nature that points toward the future and
that if you know this statement um if
you run it through your through the
wheels of your mind you have the ability
to anticipate the so-called
future uh to continue again because I
teach the importance of
knowing the meaning of the words and the
importance of using Common Sense
terminology here is what we mean by
Evolution it is a sequence of changes in
flow flow configuration in time freedom
freedom is not some intangible it is
actual
physical features that allow a system to
change and freedom can be measured uh in
uh design um freedom is measured in
terms of the number of degrees of
freedom the number of ways in which you
can change something uh Freedom can also
be measured in terms of the effect of
increasing these this number of degrees
of freedom has on the performance on the
ability of the Mover to move more easily
you can think of it as um uh okay
straight jacketing the flow of a of a
river well that River will flow uh um
less fast meaning slower and um not as
far as a river that's uh uh not straight
jaged in fact the river that's straight
jaged has a a uh a personality of its
own to revolt and remove the obstacles
out of the way the Fallen Tre log the
levies at at New
Orleans the history of the of of Earth
is is is that it is about removing
obstacles uh in order to secure greater
freedom for what moves and this
evolutionary design um as I just
Illustrated facilitates access access to
flow in areas volume volumes and that of
course includes
Society now access I checked the
dictionary although I shouldn't have to
because I come from a Latin based
language it means the action of coming
toward or near something it comes from
aesus AED in in Latin it is a word
available in English and this movement
Naturally by itself untouched uh tends
toward an architecture that's
multiscale uh it's called hierarchy or
arborescent if you will um it is a
drawing um um that distinguishes itself
through a few large channels uh
cohabitating with many small channels in
fact they're moving the same stuff and
they're moving it in harmony the few are
not exploiting the many uh the
many uh are not revolting against the
few they're all flowing together in
order to facilitate flow over the entire
available space and this configuration
um Springs out of nowhere it is nature
itself um my beginning in this um line
of thinking was in actually it was
before
1996 uh the problem that um U got got my
publishing going is here on in the left
left hand corner it was the question of
how to shape a rectangular space that
generates heat how to shape it so that
the uh the generated Heat current um
exits with greatest ease that means uh
it is rejected by a rectangle that has
the that is the the least hot meaning
with the smallest temperature difference
between itself and the ambient and in
other words I gave myself one degree of
Freedom which is the shape of the
rectangle a shape that varied from
Square to shallow rectangle the answer
to my question was the U the the the
rectangle in the in the middle which is
not too shallow not too Square um but
that was the click because from freedom
to change something I discovered one
drawing before this exercise when I
posed the problem of how to shape it I
not knowing the answer I did not have a
drawing and you see in predicting
Evolution the the thinking begins with a
blank pain age it is a the most honest
kind of beginning meaning the least
biased way in which to start to start
posing questions uh that uh that
beginning is is a has a chapter a
chapter with a blank page called the
chapter is called I don't know you see I
don't know but I discovered this and the
rest is history and in um in the year
2000 I wrote the First full length book
uh about the multitude of examples of
this type ranging from geophysics river
basins lightning and everything
snowflakes to u to physiology um
breathing uh uh blood circulation
ejaculation all these things are in in
um in accord with with the Constructor
law and um and then since then um I've
shown a few other things that I will
illustrate but the the the most
important message from this beginning is
that in science in science um quite
often uh the first question is
overlooked and the first question should
be what is the phenomenon meaning what
what what are we talking about and uh in
the case of design in nature the
phenomenon is meaning the elephant in
the uh in the room is the evolution of
flow configuration it could be the room
it could be the field or or the ocean in
other words ocean in other words nature
itself so um that phenomenon is change
with direction also known as uh uh the
passing of
time now uh getting closer to the
subject of interest of these um um vas
these hierarchical architectures are can
be simple or complex here I have uh two
drawings of the same kind of flow it is
a flow that connects one point with many
many points on a on a
circle um if I in the uh first uh dis
design on the left the um the um the
maker of the design had a very large
number of degrees of freom they are
called L and and fi and Gamma and beta
and X
uh look and that took three years to do
uh in the course of a doctoral thesis uh
it's called The Perfect Design and then
on the right one example that uh was
done a lot faster by um by recognizing
very few degrees of freedom called
capital
L and on the next Slide the performance
of these two designs the perfect shown
as black dots
and the uh cheaper one uh with the white
squares uh that performance is plotted
with this lowercase f which is a a
number proportional to the flow
resistance between the center and the
perimeter and on the obsa this capital L
is the number of points on the perimeter
which means that the uh migrating to the
right the design is more
complex um you see here that um the two
the two drawings are in fact uh they may
look different even though they are both
point to Circle trees uh but their
performance is quite quite similar quite
similar in other words a a simpler and
cheaper design will do you see uh in
other words the the maker of the design
does not waste
time the M of design is wise
than the one that uh that polishes a um
what was this sorry that gilds a the
Lily you see um and um and that leads to
uh to another uh way to organize the
presentation which is that um if you if
you polish something at infinum you're
are not creating nothing so Perfection
is the enemy of evolution this is a a
dictum from volte originally
it happens to be true from the point of
view of the Constructor law um in
fact uh I I discovered it but I also
discovered the the first the first
Discoverer in this Cas bter because I'm
a fan of the history of good ideas and
here's how the uh the eny the enemy
Evolution if you know it uh benefits us
uh the movement of people on the surface
of the Earth is hierarchical we don't
move around tracing the Grid on the
surface of the city we congregate We
Gather uh we collect ourselves to one
point of Attraction um use your
imagination you know Public Square um
and then at the end of the event we
migrate outward to the area as a
circular River
delta and in so doing we organize our
society
hierarchically uh here is an even better
example of how it is going because you
see in the previous drawing which is the
simplest possible this city block does
not show the smallest alleys and the
cucks and the uh The Lawns across which
people walk but here in the uh drawing
of the Atlanta airport uh we see the
walking this is on left side vertically
along the
concourses um the uh the vehicle there's
only one train shown as a black line um
the by the way once again uh the the
slow and the fast are carrying the same
the same flow meaning the same crowd of
people access is provided from any gate
to any other gate and uh the figure of
Merit where the performance of the hole
I'm talking about the whole the whole
flow system which is
rectangular uh can be measured in
several ways one of them is the average
travel time uh between one gate and all
the other Gates so keep that in mind
travel time averaged over the area
that's uh the measure of performance um
the movement is with two speeds um fast
along the train uh slower perpendicular
to the
train any one of us is is this capital
letter q and um and the territory is has
a is has a fixed size because area costs
money but a variable shape a variable
ratio of h ided l it is possible to show
um almost on the back of an envelope uh
how the um average travel time depends
on the shape uh time is on the ordinate
uh the shape is on the abissa and you
see here a bucket shaped curve which has
a minimum shown as a an empty circle uh
the shape at that location is called h /
by L
Optimum and the time is minimum at that
in that particular design the um the
discovery meaning to put
physics uh at the disposal of vol is
that a little bit of imperfection
meaning uh travel time that's just
slightly longer than the smallest
imaginable uh give the gives the
designer a significant bandwidth of um
of freedom freedom to choose a shape
that's okay comparable with the
mathematically best shape but not
exactly the same in fact the person who
is empowered sorry endowed with this
kind of secret uh will not spend time on
finessing this particular SC sculpture
to the point of identifying the the
absolute best so imperfection
imperfection or the the freedom the
freedom of of choosing and then moving
on is the mother of diversity in nature
diversity happens from this freedom
freedom not to be U uh not to fall in
love with the absolute best and um there
are people in several domains including
biology who who talk about nature makes
makes mistakes no nature doesn't make
mistakes nature simply doesn't have time
to to focus on on finessing itself uh
what works is kept that is the slogan
that I think uh uh comes closer to how
nature
Works uh one um aspect of um of movement
of geophysical biological and also human
is uh is the so-called the logistics S
curve um anything that spreads freely on
an area or in a volume uh it spreads not
only in space you can imagine the uh the
milk spilled on the kitchen floor it
spreads in time and the the invaded
territory which in these Rising curves
is indicated in the vertical Direction
This invaded territory grows in S curve
fashion it grows uh slow fast slow and
uh the reason for that by the way here
are a few more examples that are
relevant to what I'm going to show you
next uh these are ual measurements every
single curve is an S curve on the left
is the power production in the United
States uh as an S curve um that is up to
10 years ago uh on the right are the
total miles driven in the US uh per year
and um at the very bottom are the the
movers themselves meaning the world
population that is also so an S curve
which um um is already hitting the the
ceiling the ceiling I remember when I
was a an undergraduate in
1970 uh the rage was uh about the fact
that there's a population
explosion and uh the end of uh the end
of oil and lots of other things of this
kind um well um as I said at the
beginning humility plays a role in
science um it's much much more useful
for The Thinker to start with I'm not so
sure I'm not so sure let me look into it
even if I believed these things uh it's
very important that I qu I'm the I I I I
am the first to question
them and the reason why the S curve
should be an S and it is predictable is
this
uh anything that spreads again the milk
on the kitchen floor initially it
invades the
territory as something that moves fast
and far and narrow like a
finger and once the finger hits the the
wall the wall uh the in this case the
milk spreads
laterally uh I call I call these two
phases of of the
occupation by using words from the
military Invasion and then
consolidation it's always this way and
well but as you can see in the uh lower
right hand corner um Invasion invades
the area at an accelerate accelerating
uh
rate and consolidation continues at a
decelerating rate and uh so these two
arcs are spiced together obviously
naturally and together they make up the
S curve so this is the prediction the
where does the um the hierarchy come in
the hierarch hierarchy um is an addon
meaning the next slide which I don't
have uh which is that things that spread
on a Surface spread in arborescent
fashion not as a single needle as in
this particular example and the the the
the tree the tree spreads the stuff even
faster than what I Illustrated here in
other words something that spreads as a
tree will have an S that that is taller
during its uh um uh viral
viral Intero you see and um so let's see
that's basically
the uh the
um let's call it the the Preparatory uh
material for for uh showing us who we
are um the movement the movement of I
this is an image of human movement today
it is primarily primarily uh due to
Aviation Aviation uh we all move on the
globe from any point to any other point
imaginable
um Those Who U uh originate from let's
say diametrically opposed points uh
necessarily will have to flow through
the heart of this vascular architecture
the heart is where this architecture was
born which was uh Europe and North
America uh and that is where the
architecture has grown the most which is
why it is in deep red right now and um
so the movement is
hierarchical the um the physics of
movement is that to move more you must
burn more fuel so the burning of fuel on
the globe must be hierarchical meaning
I'm looking at this image and I read the
movement I'm another Adrian reads the
burning of fuel and as you'll see next
the burning of fuel is in fact
proportional to the to the the to the
wealth wealth available on the on the
globe as in have money will travel and
also on the next slide I'll show you
that uh increasing hand inand with
wealth and fuel use and movement is
freedom and uh that's this is the final
slide on the left hand side is the uh
these are the facts these are data um
people today like to uh to uh who pray
to into in in the Church of data and
data well here's data these are the
facts uh those dots show that every
group on the uh on the globe falls on
the diagonal between energy use and an
annual wealth which means that what is
annual use of energy in physics en
engineering is uh just another uh
language uh in which to tell tell the
story of of hierarchical distribution of
wealth on the globe meaning that
economics and and the physics are two
sides of the same qu of the same coin
meaning two ways in which to describe
the same drawing and the drawing is
hierarchical um all these dots are
racing upward along the diagonal because
as everybody knows every government
reports annually uh its increase in GDP
in in wealth well the government doesn't
brag about the increase in the burning
of fuel which of course means that no
country is going to cut down uh its
consumption of fuel um and on the right
hand in other words the red arrow the
direction of the bicycl and the pelaton
in the two the France is the future on
the right hand side the same data with
the annual energy use on this time on
the ordinate and on the obsa the the
competitiveness with regard to economic
freedom the the arrow that points toward
the future is the same as on the left
hand side the dots are the same as on
the left hand side and they tell the
story of a world uh that another p of
bicyclists that are racing upward even
though most most governments don't know
it uh that the evolution of the Society
of the globe is toward not only greater
movement easier movement but also
greater
freedom and that takes me to the slide
that Susan showed you um the um the the
mother if I were to say the mother
father of nature is uh in this direction
from freedom of Change Is Possible from
change evolution is
possible and From Evolution the nature
that we are and the which surrounds us
um has become possible as well thank
you thank
you Susan would you like to provide a
first reflection or Direction
here um well before um it evaporates uh
you were shaking your head so much Danel
I want to see what's alive for
you I wrote down many things I have many
questions to ask so but please feel free
to ask one first and I'll prepar okay
okay um what what really stood out for
me um and I'm I'm slightly Prejudice
because I've been going through the the
physics of life so you that's uh the so
many so many um ideas are captured in
that but what really stands out for me
Adrian is um is I'm
seeing the system as
object
and structure as a
verb no structure structure is a noun um
structure is a um um it comes from the
same word
as well has the same origin as the word
stun stun meaning uh Spread spread of in
this case on a on a page or on a canvas
uh it's a drawing it's a drawing with
with a message streaming out of it so
structure is um is a to structure is a
verb clearly most most of uh this is now
in the um uh in the languages of the
indans tend to have both they could be
both noun and verb that um is a is a
feature of this group of languages but I
don't think it's limited to the induran
the point is that uh um yes I
applaud everybody's interest in the
meaning of the words because quite
frankly um we are surrounded where we're
actually drowning in
jargon uh jargon is a good term it
applies for uh it applies to uh locker
room discussion I language that's
understood only by 20 people all of them
men you see um yes it's just like like
any uh Department of physics oops sorry
I didn't mean to put it that way but uh
you get the idea uh the uh the object
here which is why I continue to praise
Galo galile and D Vinci and these people
the object is to to make these uh these
ideas or AAS are accessible to uh to
everybody to everybody it doesn't mean
to dilute them or to dumb them not at
all it means it means it means to
display humidity and to speak in a way
not only to speak but to make drawings
that uh that Open the Eyes of people and
I'm fortunate because as a professor I
have this freedom to in fact I just
lectured today the freedom to make
drawings the freedom to to we yes to
tell a joke every once in a while um
maybe a self-deprecating joke the point
is that the uh uh the the flow of
science the flow of science benefits
from um from um first of all modesty but
also the ability to uh ask questions and
the to question the idea but to question
the the speaker including
yourself so so let me let me do that now
um um and and help me understand where
I'm confused because I guess I'm when I
say the structure is verb I'm thinking
about how we're talking
about um configuration and
reconfiguration and um and how the
drawing actually turns into a
movie oh that you know that I can get a
you know my head around um and um and
specifically you know what what I'm
where I'm grappling with this and it's
opening doors is how to think about you
using the Constructor law the difference
specifically between the tree
structure which to me is
shape and and the S
curve and that is time so when I'm
thinking about reconfiguration help me
understand you where you when I'm
thinking about movement and flow and the
configuration the
architecture um how you know how is that
informing me well where am I well okay a
um a hierarchical drawing like the uh
the River Basin uh has U many many
shapes the biggest is the shape of the
page inside of it there's the shape of
the angle between two
tributaries uh the drawing is full of
such angles those angles are all
different well but at the same time
they're all similar because they're all
kind of close to 75 de or
50° um so you have shapes Galore if you
if you if you if that is what interests
you others others are interested in
lengths well there are many channels and
the the lengths are themselves
hierarchical some are you know longer
others are shorter um the um the more of
these let's call them shapes and lengths
uh the more complex the drawing is and
complex you have to be very careful with
this word is one that uh that
um that places the discussion closer to
the locker room meaning the the jargon
because it hides hides these elements
that I was uh enumerating uh complex the
word itself means uh means Twisted
together and um well that's if I use
that word I I declare defeat not Victory
you see if it's twisted
together I don't even I cannot even wish
myself good luck because there is no
luck um in any case I know what it means
and to me a word like that uh is an
invitation to to question to question
the word to question the speaker to ask
myself what is the drawing that's come
complex if you ask if you ask this
question you discover that the drawing
is not that complex because if if you
can if you can make it it it is not not
Twisted together you see it is Twisted
together uh meaning um like one of
these truly fractal drawings when you
cannot draw it you
see uh so on and on look we can we can
uh let's say uh uh uh slice the orange
here and small slices but we're wasting
our time if we do that the point is that
um to answer you the words that uh we
use are very useful but uh they also
tend to to u to to separate us to keep
us apart if we do not agree on their
meaning and that's why I interject Ed
and I I added some imagery to the words
that you
speaking okay and by the way structure
same origin as stun well that's where
the scurve phenomenon is you know the
the spreading is as curve uh that's
growth also known as growth um the
collecting is also as curved uh which is
also growth you know during the the the
the reaping of harvest the the flow of
the grain from the area to The
Silo is a stream that grows slow fast
slow um the direction of the flow is not
the phenomenon the history of the flow
is the phenomenon and it is called the S
curve um also known as the logistics uh
S curve or the logistics curve and and
um I can tell you the history of that if
you're interested the point is that
Logistics come from a military
military um what's the word um yeah they
call Logistics the the flow of material
uh food not just ammunition but uh
mobile hospitals and the infirmaries and
all these things that are flowing and
moving uh behind behind the troops um
and um there's a great quote
from Napoleon Napoleon bonapart U he
said uh um amateur he was talking about
generals amateurs talk talk strategy
professionals talk
Logistics Logistics and uh that was
Napoleon uh the quote is even better
known because of the English language as
belonging to General Omar Bradley
uh who used it without crediting
Napoleon so so but in any case these are
two very important figures who knew uh
which end is up think about it highly
successful uh because you see it today
in in the conflicts that are raging it's
not about what goes on not meaning not
only what goes on on the on the front it
is about the um Logistics where the the
the the the the the power of the society
behind behind the um the uh the military
activity this is extremely important to
uh to to to learn from every uh news
item
today well thank you I I'll give a
reflection and connect just a few areas
of flow that that I think really speak
to some of the points so the key
reflection is nature is not broken by
Department it's not broken or mistaken
in any way and that is
radically different than many
organizational structures including in
learning and education and so that's a
big question mark in a big open space
and then there was some pictures and
some words and some symbols but that's a
starting place that's perennial um I
thought of two kind of
flows evoked in your description the
first was drawing with a ballpoint pen
on the page and the ink as it
diffuses through the paper and about how
there's a trace and then there's you
could imagine filling the channels of
the paper and different properties of
the paper and just about how the act of
drawing is and and why the line fixes at
a certain point that's the S curve has
flowed to its flow it dri solvent is
gone so on so you can go into more
detail but just in that act and then
another one perhaps more in a
informational space is the jargon and
the jargon can be
piercing but it can be a grappling hook
to go 100 miles out and get really
specific I'm talking about Theta sub
Delta of figure four of your 2012 paper
and that can go all the way down and
then there's that second phase of
expansion it's not just about throwing
needles it's about throwing the needle
to the wall that was your engineered
setting and then if it makes contact
then there's this secondary phase that's
the actual
Overture and the
initial
precision technical
detail is a first Contact if even that
and again that gives Science Education
and practice I think a
real Challenge and
opportunity uh I think you hit the the
nail on the head three three times real
hard and it's the same uh is the same
nail uh even though every time you it
made the issued a different screen um
the um but that is in fact very accurate
very accurate and it happens just a
second and and it does happen the way
that you uh you professed uh it does
happen even after it hits the wall in
all your examples because because
happening is nature itself um the U the
the let's say the campus divided into
departments that don't talk to each
other is
unnatural it's
unnatural uh these barriers have been uh
uh disregarded by by clear by clear
thinkers uh all the time the ones who
have made progress or contributions are
the professors or researchers that had
the inate ability to to uh to to scale
fences and jump over them or to get
drunk and step off the curb and fall on
the street uh these are the people who
made the history of science uh they the
name they are called polymaths okay and
U we have them I know even here at Duke
I know the the few who are who are this
way they are my friends and um and uh
we're we're too busy to start a
revolution but the the future is uh the
way the way you you sketched it it will
be it will continue to be one of filling
in the spaces or rediscovering or
repeating what others have done in the
sketchy fashion or maybe throwing a
jargon word out there or perhaps as a
joke as a joke or or even uh even more
effective as a non PC joke and then
people say ah
Aha and then and um in the beginning the
this act this act the this spark you you
described
um takes roots and fills the space
because because a good idea is like food
for the hungry it attracts it attracts
participants it attracts students it
attracts disciples followers second
generation teachers or artists and I'll
come back to your first example when
when you started speaking I saw
immediately the history of painting the
first thing that DaVinci and these
people Michelangelo did was to make a a
very fast pencil
sketch something that only they
recognized because it was already in
their minds and today with all this
instrumentation people are discovering
as traces of graffiti on the on the
canvas that had been covered much later
with with various colors over and over
again yes that's the way that's the way
nature really works and um and nature is
also the brain itself let's face it
there's no other there's no other
architecture that works except the one
that I've have sketched crudely in my uh
in my uh Exposition
here
Susan do you want to give a kind of
closing question or comment while we
have
Adrien I'm I'm gonna begin with a blank
slate I I'm I'm I'm I'm available a
little longer if you if you have a food
for the hungry here
oh I'll ask a question from the live
chat if if all right yeah
upcycle Club writes a question to
Professor Bon what are the biggest
unanswered questions or areas of
exploration within constructal theory
that you hope future researchers will
investigate good question well uh the
I've been kicking this ball um for um
what almost 40 years um not uh not in
the direction of discovering uh the
Biggers that need to be discovered or to
be explored but out of
curiosity today as youve saw in Susan's
presentation there's a world movement
it's populated primarily by by younger
people who are in fact competing with me
uh clearly I'm I'm not at the start of
my career but they are beginning and in
fact they're quite uh creative and uh
productive um the
um my own uh new work is about uh uh
asking questions that about this field
that have not
been asked or
answered uh the constructed law has not
been refuted by anyone in its uh you
know
already four decades nobody so I decided
to question it myself
to say listen let me uh what was that
word let me
um
uh uh let me prove it wrong but there's
this word from Carl popper about
falsification yeah yeah let me let me
falsify
okay and so I I'm looking for phenomena
that at first uh viewing seemed to
contradict the Constructor law
yes and uh because I have the talent of
looking around and uh and um yeah I keep
my eyes open yes uh when there's a heavy
downpour and the the rain falls on um on
dirt the um the the obviously the river
River Basin is born but the river
channels uh flow um with cataract
they develop a
periodic um sequence of little pools
in inter space with the manyi
waterfalls
cataract yes the river is uh putting the
brakes on
itself yes it's a contradiction of the
constructed
law right so I questioned it and I
published it and I discovered in the
course of U uh proving The Constructor
law wrong The Constructor law is right
the water that flows in a periodic
fashion flows faster than uh in the
textbook of water flowing uniformly and
steadily down an incline of
a along a inclined plane
uh and the reason the reason why the
interrupted flow is faster is there's a
there's nothing nothing more um perfect
for the flow of water than to fall
without friction to fall over a
dam so the water the water well the
water and the erodable soil have in them
in themselves this tendency called
freedom freedom to facilitate
access and I uh I
uh I was yes I was excited to not that
not to prove myself right I was actually
trying to find the um limited
applicability of this of this concept uh
and in this case I did not find it and I
I'm continuing this sort of I'm um I'm
the okay in the same rum I'm both you
know prophet and G fly I'm trying to
prove prove Adrian wrong okay and uh
it's exciting but uh I'm a I'm an
audience of one uh I talk to my wife and
she knows where I'm coming from and uh
all of it is worth is worth laughing in
fact but if we don't laugh uh we uh we
have no future
frankly so just to kind of wrap up the
um I think I read the paper you're
talking about but I remember uh
something about the
edes um and
cor and yeah and that kind of brought me
back to what you know what Daniel's
question was about is far as you know
how we break free these
silos um and you how does how does that
how does that
form um and also I think that also um
speaks to maybe the second session that
we can hold which is about the freedom
because you we really that is of itself
that's a topic that is just so
rich I'm happy you mention the edies
because that was an earlier um um
example of uh U my questioning this this
principle people all over people all
over view
turbulence especially in in the applied
World turbulence is something bad
something that increases friction um yes
yes something that's um not as good as
the smooth flow called laminer flow uh
the one with the smooth streamlines and
this is what you see in the text
yeah turbulence this complicated thing
you know edies rubbing
and well you know what turbulent flow is
constructal as well because because
compared with a lamina turbulent flow uh
uh answers the question of what really
flows What flows is not the fluid What
flows is the movement across the fluid
meaning the movement from the
fast to the slow in other words the
mixing the mixing is the mixing is known
in physics as the transfer of momentum
uh that is what's facilitated by this St
change in the drawing from smooth uh
layers to to things that appear to be
complicated but by the way they're not
complicated when I did predict the sizes
of these edes and their speeds and their
hierarchy they are hierarchical the
edies the edies are basically these
trees the trees that I drew uh like the
Trees of a River Basin uh but the the
the River Basin that becomes this
turbulent pool is a is a is a tree the
channels of which are embedded in in the
in the same fluid which which is the the
the pool and uh every CH every channel
uh is unstable and becomes curved
becomes an Edie and it rolls over and um
the the uh the the tree that I just
sketched uh becomes a bouquet a bouquet
of broken branches that continue to roll
they continue to roll filling the space
but you can see their birth in in the
little speech that I gave um and in any
case there's a hierarchy of edes in
every so-called turbulent flow field now
the doctrine of turbulence research is
not like what I just spoke it is about a
a uniform distribution over the field
over the pool of EDS of various sizes as
if there are
uh uh you know fruits of various sizes
all thrown into a pot and mixed around
with with the chocolate sauce you know
uh that's not what turbulence is
turbulence is a is a broken tree
structure the branches of which keep
rolling uh embedded in each other and uh
and that that so-called mixture is the
one that Vehicles the movement of
movement across the the
volume without it without it um without
it there would be no uh frankly without
turbulence there would be no life on
Earth uh everything would be stagnant
pool of I don't know what a layer a
layer of no life uh and then another
layer of no life and a you know in other
words no mixing the by the way so mixing
we know this from other stories of
Science and History mixing is in fact
um the mother of not only life that's
you get species from uh from from um
events of of encounter you know
encounter or
meeting um and um new species from for
example from inter breathing and so on
and um so without mixing there's nothing
on Earth
nothing so one final question um that
speaks back to your slide on nothing
moves unless it's
pushed
yeah that's
right that's is if one us to explain
explain that uh
yeah a peasant knows that the horse is
needed
don't need only a card um and I come
back to uh through uh the news of the
day the um
um the the logistics the the ability to
move things the ability to power things
this is uh this
is Extreme I would say is the most
important because Society itself is
alive because of the of the power that
it the society
produces and that the power by the way
something else that people don't realize
is spent as soon as it is produced it is
spent and and destroyed dissipated as
soon as it is made and that is called
movement or life life means to destroy
this the power that is available to you
you don't have to look at today's
Advanced Society look at any animal any
animal um the movement of the animal is
the
physical movie of how the U the um
useful energy embodied in the in the
food is being
destroyed uh no food no animal
movement simple as that no food and no
um engine which is the animal itself
that means death not
life
death and uh these are basic facts of
physics you don't need an education
and whatever anthropology or uh yeah you
could use an an education in a
veterinarian medicine that's where you
get this much broader picture of Who We
Are
um thank you Adrien we really
appreciated it hope to talk to you
another
time all right thank you thank you for
the opportunity to uh get to know each
other thank you yes thank you so
much very insightful thank you well
Susan I have many random remarks to
share would you like to share anything
you go ahead go ahead and of course
what's going on in the in the
chat yeah all right I'll I'll read a few
um traveling fast and slow that reminded
me of thinking fast and slow and then in
the airport there was the fast backbone
and the slow walking on the
edges but in terms of thinking fast and
slow actually the fast part is on the
edges of the biological organ ISM with
the reflexes and the reactivity and the
slower part is the backbone so it's like
kind of the same but different um
another piece was he said that the first
question is often overlooked like what
phenomena are we looking at what's the
system of interest and then that made me
think about like biomechanics like an
elbow moving and so in the physics
textbook or in a example it's like well
there's a weight on the end of a stiff
rod and it's set up but that's kind of
The Last Mile question the phenomena of
the arm is a broader phenomena and so
you still may want to have that very
reduced disciplinary
model it's small it's useful it can give
insight and so on it's just part of a
bigger tapestry about that
phenomena and that's a different
starting point for the conversation and
the
collaboration on that topic that's not
disciplinary so the entry point of the
real system and the entry and returning
point is by definition the broader
conversation than the kind of terminal
scientific artifact which as we
discussed that's kind of the narrow but
far as opposed to the broader and and
kind of softer
but more space
enclosing yes and actually that brings
up
um you when you think about
phenomenon um yeah I almost want to go
to you know what is the context but
phenomenon is actually you know what is
Flowing what you know what so when we
kind of pull that in as far as the Fast
and the slow
how
much and you know a lot of
times by injecting that you're actually
putting
turbulence into a
conversation which you know which if
somebody is um associating turbulence
with conflict then they might be
actually distorting it
extorting the freedom of what can
emerge um and so you know this comes
back to the you know Invasion
acceleration he spoke about and then the
consolidation is the
deceleration yeah a few few points on
that first I think a question I'd love
to learn more about is like Trends are
not
monotonic so just because things have
been a certain way for the last 50 or
100 years doesn't even mean the sign is
going to be the same so I'd be
interested to see how that kind of
change comes into play but I'm thinking
about a cars engine there's Parts where
the laminer flow is the desirable trait
for transfer and then there's Parts
where mixing like liquid and gas and
thermal mixing is more
important and they simply are not the
functional they play complimentary
functional roles it's literally like
fast and slow and there's never a reason
why especially considered apart from a
specific system it basically can't be
said which of those Tendencies are you
know even you know how to compare them
which is why even though we were looking
at a two-dimensional shape with the
rectangle there was only one degree of
Freedom which was the
ratio so that reflects I think having a
simple we need to capture that yeah yeah
capture
that yeah this this actually so if we
were to translate this and you bring in
some active inference you what's kind of
coming alive for me in this is the
difference between exploration and
exploitation yeah like he showed a a
parabola with a ball y rolling to the
bottom of the hill and then there was
kind of a a zone of tolerance like
within 10% of the Y AIS and so it pretty
shallow bowl wide Bowl so there was a
lot of play that would keep it within a
10% Tolerance on the white now to
persistently optimize that all the ball
needs to know is the slope of which
direction it should head it given that
it's already knowing that it's within
this zone of control ability which is
how all bodies are everyone has you know
been part of an unbroken chain of blood
sugar regulation so the evolutionary and
the developmental prior is that the
physiological state is already in the
zone of control and then it's just a
directional issue to head towards the
bottom of the bowl but you can't
stop X Change You Can't Stop climate
from changing you can't stop physiology
from changing that's not to say you
can't drisk and think about real
consequences of action but just taking
it at the
most narrow technical sense of change
through time and evolution all things
are changing there's no point in trying
to Halt
change and it's a simpler actionable
heris for the ball on the ball uh bottom
of the bowl which way is the free energy
flowing
yep have the least resistance um and and
you this kind of comes back to the
phenomenon of how do we
predict um
and
um and in fact I would suggest let me
share my screen because for those people
listening um yes I just uh go for it see
yeah do you see it
so yeah I mean just putting that you
being able I I const I constantly go
back to and reread this law in fact the
reason I'd said earlier that I'm going
back
to a clean slate because it was like you
know whenever I whenever I have the
opportunity to speak with Adrian he puts
something out there and I'm
like
so what I thought you I was reading into
it it was kind of yeah that's kind of
going to that the phenomenon of
exploration um and you know seeing
what's out there you know how are we
perceiving the world right um and um and
then how do we switch
to exploitation and when I'm saying
exploitation I'm talking about how do we
move from being in the world to how do
we move to remaking the world or or or
changing you doing what he talked about
originally is is how do we um how do we
construct um the the um the world around
us for you know for our Niche
construction actually he does reference
Niche Construction in the book um and uh
and so how do we you how do we do that
so that we're using the least amount of
necessary energy because I think that
one question that I had which I think
would be a a um topic for a future
conversation is is how do we know when
we are um violating the Constructor
law yeah and this ties back
to the belief
updating if I could I'd like to connect
a few of the words you have on this
slide to the ACM ontology and that's
kind of like as we explore all the time
that's how we kind of begin that
bidirectional conversation so like for a
finite size system that is a thing
system of interest it's a thing it's the
blanket and the internal states of the
particular partition the particle the
thing itself to persist in time non
equilibrium steady state or a
similar phrasing talking about the path
of least action of the stationary State
or the attractor or the trajectory or
the path of that thing MH so we're
talking about the same kind of system of
interest and then evolve with freedom as
we heard these terms are
plain and so evolve being changed
Through Time notably not taking on the
kind of
intergenerational connotation of
evolution some people like in biology
would say something like well Evolution
happens between gener generations and
development and ecology happens within a
generation but here time evolution is
being used more generally Freedom was
described in terms of degrees of freedom
statistics degrees of freedom and we
could also think about rule-based
degrees of freedom as affordances as the
knobs that can be changed those are the
degrees of freedom on that
interface and then to the last piece the
providing easier and greater access to
What flows here I um think to the recent
guest stream
63.1 that discussed the philosophical
status of material and information
flows and moral Logistics yes and then
of course the the the joke I guess was
like the logistic curve but it's like
logistic and Logistics and then what
status to Accord to material flows and
informational Flows In integrated
autopoetic
mortal computational systems where
there's a weaving of like the blood flow
of the brain and the ion flow and the
nutrients and there's an informational
flow semantic flow that is not strictly
described by the material
architecture now now to pull back to
to okay so put that in the frame of
reference
in terms of one thing he said that was
like blew my mind
was um it's not the it's not
the what is flowing when he was
referencing what is flowing and I'm you
know and so what you just
said
um where I'm going with this and you if
this if tell me if if this is where
you're thinking
is
epistemic and pragmatic
value
so what is Flowing I mean once we we can
calculate
that and he also gave a a calculation
for degrees of
freedom nice these are great directions
I'll I'll just go to a different angle I
thought it was I loved his recurrent
connection with drawing and art and
about the sketches that are being
discovered behind paintings that's like
deeper blankets of the painting deeper
levels of historical meaning and cross
cross referencing like oh this one is
signed at an earlier date and we have
this letter so we know that they were
speaking with this person so it's like
deeper in space and time and
causality and then even our artist like
Kandinsky would go through many
iterations and many sketches on even
nonrepresentational or
post-representational however you want
to think about the kind of art that's
not like a landscape but the painting
was then synesthetic with the
auditory and so that kind of brings
together not to resolve but for the
beauty of the snapshot the noun
structure
and the Dynamics to structure as a verb
and as a process and like the fact that
you can't
disentangle or drop one or the other
prioritize one or the other they're
literally snapshots of the
movie Yes yes and and to kind of tie
that back
to um you the path of leas action
and
um and but it reminds me of a saying and
correct me correct if correct me if I'm
not getting this correct but yeah the
difference
between um the saying goes is the
difference between an average artist and
a and a expert or a master artist is
knowing when to paint the last paint
strke that's cool it reminds me of I
would have written a shorter letter if I
had more time like there's these kind of
are they intuitive or are they
counterintuitive because it's knowing
what not to do and when to do it yeah
yes yes and this yeah this yes yeah
that's that's a that's a great uh way
to uh to wrap that up yeah because it
comes back
to you know
the the the path of least resistance and
you know and the and the
freedom and so often times the
affordances if people don't understand
that you they're actually pushing too
hard or overdesigning
um and you how do we how do we use the
Constructor law and active
inference
to to to his point I mean it's like
power is spent as soon as it's produced
I'll make a few more contact points with
active inference one question I have is
like where's the
Observer we've explored a lot this year
with Chris fields's course in the
quantum information sciences and so on
about the role of the Observer
so should we think of these flow
processes as only or actually occurring
on the material substrate if so where is
the space for the Observer or the poly
Computing of Mike so that's one open
question and then I think another
important touch point is like Notions of
hierarchy which he returned to and there
was like a very unconventional hierarchy
represented with people's diffusion from
city blocks like smaller and bigger
parties getting going to and leaving at
different times and then the diffusion
Maps across the city and so it's like
that's one representation he kind of
contrasted that flow hierarchy with like
a pyramid um type representation maybe
you mentioned this and then that made me
think about two ways that we see the
hierarchical models in active inference
one of them that are different than both
the pyramid and the um city blocks one
of them is the spatial enclosure nested
blankets nested models that are
enclosing each other not just diffusing
into the same city and then another is
the
metacognitive with the word of saned
Smith at all in live stream 28 with the
hierarchical model representing
metacognitive
layers so between the pyramid the city
streets the enclosure and the mind that
one symbol Bridges us already such that
it puts the Bruns of the question on
what to do and how to do it yeah yeah
lot so much to expl makes that's
exciting uh so to wrap up and to capture
is there any other questions not that we
have to answer them now but if you can
you just kind of read off any other
questions that might have shown up in
the live chat I'll capture those and you
know and we can start kind of a
repository of what you know what showed
up today um and uh and that way we can
use it to explore explore further yeah
we will continue the kind of series and
the curating of questions I'll just read
one Mills 8102 wrote what are the
factors or conditions that afford the
restructuring of a flow system does it
always require the imposition of
sufficient Demand on that system to
change does it take a
crisis great question and one one
question I have is where are perception
and
action do you have any last comments or
thoughts just my head
spinning wow well wow great thank you
Susan and thank
you farewell yes till next time
absolutely
bye